{"tossups": [{"question": "This leader had ten soldiers escort Charles Maclean to Delagoa Bay, leading to accusations that Maclean was a spy. According to Donald Morris, this man executed seven thousand people for not being adequately grief-stricken after the death of his mother, Nandi. Nathaniel Isaacs was named the principal chief of Natal by this ruler but fled due to the anticipated massacre of white citizens by Dingane [[din-GAH-neh]]. An advocate for a short spear called an <em>iklwa</em> [[ICK-lwah]], for the point, who was this leader of the Zulu people?", "answer": "<b><u>Shaka</u></b> Zulu (accept Shaka <b><u>kaSenzangakhon</u></b>; accept Sigidi <b><u>kaSenzangakhon</u></b>; prompt on \"Zulu\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "According to legend, this thinker's mother moved to three different places while searching for a suitable place to raise him. This thinker claimed that virtue could be cultivated from four \"sprouts\" of goodness. This man's namesake book was collected as the final one of the Four Books by Zhu Xi [[ZHOO SHEE]]. This student of Zisi [[ZEE-SEE]] demonstrated the goodness of humanity with the example of saving a child from a well. For the point, name this Chinese philosopher, known as the \"Second Sage\" of Confucianism.", "answer": "<b><u>Mencius</u></b> (or <b><u>Meng</u></b> Ke; or <b><u>Meng</u></b>zi)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This city was denied the right to veto royal interventions in religious affairs in the 1581 Treaty of Drohiczyn [[drah-HEET-sheen]]. This city was the center of a \"National Awakening\" inspired by the efforts of Ernest Blanks and Rainis. This city is connected to J\u016brmala [[YUHR-mah-lah]] by the K\u0101rlis Ulmanis highway, named for a pre-World War Two prime minister. Albert of Livonia founded this city after Hartwig, Archbishop of Bremen, sent him on a crusade. The Russian Baltic Fleet fought in a 1915 battle on a gulf named for, for the point, what largest city in the Baltic states?", "answer": "<b><u>Riga</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was supported by the Popular Unity coalition, though earlier he opposed Eduardo Frei [[FRAY]] Montalva as leader of the FRAP. As president, this man supported education for the indigenous Mapuche [[mah-POO-cheh]] people and embarked on a Marxist nationalization campaign under the Vuskovich plan. During a 1973 CIA-assisted military coup, this man announced from La Moneda that he would not resign, after which he committed suicide with an AK-47. For the point, what Chilean president was ousted by Augusto Pinochet?", "answer": "Salvador <b><u>Allende</u></b> [[ah-YEN-deh]] Gossens", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This work for solo piano was arranged for a live album in 1971 by Emerson, Lake, and Palmer as well as for a ballet choreographed by Bolshoi director Alexei Ratmansky in 2014. Based on the paintings of the composer's friend, Viktor Hartmann, this 1874 creation for solo piano by a Russian composer is better known today as an orchestral piece, arranged in 1922 by a French composer. For the point, what is this suite of ten virtuoso piano pieces, written by Modest [[moh-DEST]] Mussorgsky, and later orchestrated by Maurice Ravel [[rah-VEL]]?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Pictures at an Exhibition</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The former slave Sakoura [[sah-KOO-rah]] ruled this empire before he was killed by the Afar. One of this empire's leaders may have led a fleet of ships that reached the New World, since a type of metal produced in this empire was found in Hispaniola. One of this empire's leaders, Abu Bakr II, disappeared while traveling the Atlantic, leading to the succession of a man whose gold caused a recession in Cairo. The <em>mansa</em>, Musa I, ruled, for the point, what empire governed from Timbuktu?", "answer": "<b><u>Mali</u></b>an Empire (or <b><u>Manden</u></b> Kuruowca; or <b><u>Nyeni</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The \"Red Princess\" was a woman with this name, who was the first royal confirmed to die of COVID-19. Mozart originally intended to premiere <em>Don Giovanni</em> for a woman of this name, though the <em>Marriage of Figaro</em> was substituted instead. At the Isle of the Pheasants, a woman of this name married Louis XIV, and she was part of the Pleasures of the Enchanted Island at Versailles. Friedrich Haugwitz [[HOW-gvitz]] created a standing army with a woman of this name who was succeeded by Joseph II. For the point, give this name of the only female Habsburg ruler.", "answer": "<b><u>Maria Theresa</u></b> (accept <b><u>Maria Theresa</u></b> of Spain; accept <b><u>Mar\u00eda Teresa</u></b> of Bourbon-Parma)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Lord Cornwallis supposedly called this city \u201ca hornet\u2019s nest of rebellion\u201d after an attempted ambush there. The Reed Gold Mine in this city set off the first gold rush in American history. A likely forged document supposedly signed in this city in 1775 is sometimes called the first Declaration of Independence from America, the Mecklenburg Declaration. For the point, name this Piedmont-region city, nicknamed \u201cThe Queen City\u201d because it was named after a princess of Mecklenburg-Strelitz.", "answer": "<b><u>Charlotte</u></b>, North Carolina", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "With his colleagues, this former member of the <em>Freikorps</em> was captured while attempting to flee to Urfeld by the 36th Infantry during Operation Alsos. The play <em>Copenhagen</em> by Michael Frayn explores differing versions of a 1941 meeting between this man and fellow physicist, Niels Bohr. During World War Two, this man headed the Nazi nuclear weapons program, and this scientist suggested that a particle\u2019s exact position, in relation to its momentum, cannot be determined. For the point, what German physicist formulated a namesake \u201cuncertainty principle\u201d?", "answer": "Werner <b><u>Heisenberg</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "Until 2012, Ansaru operated as a splinter group from this other organization. This organization notably targets Kanuri [[kah-NOO-ree]] people for recruitment in the Borno State. This organization's founder, Mohammed Yusuf, was executed in 2009. This organization, led by Abubakar Shekau [[sheh-KOW]], committed the kidnapping of the Chibok [[CHEE-bahk]] schoolgirls, prompting the hashtag \"BringBackOurGirls.\" In 2015, this organization became known as the Islamic State in West Africa. For the point, name this Islamic terrorist organization primarily based out of Nigeria.", "answer": "<b><u>Boko Haram</u></b> (accept <b><u>Jama'atu Ahlis Sunna Lidda'Awati Wal-Jihad</u></b>; accept <b><u>Islamic State in West Africa</u></b> before mentioned; do not accept or prompt on \"Islamic State\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "The first of these states defaced the tomb of Imam Husayn, forcing the Ottomans to execute its leader, Abdullah. The second of these states collapsed at the Battle of Mulayda after the victory of the Rashidis under Jabal Shammar. Faisal ibn Turki led one of these states, the third of which was formed when Hejaz and Najd united, creating a state which was recognized by the U.K. in the Treaty of Jeddah. Abdulaziz founded the most recent example of, for the point, what states named for the ruling family of a modern, oil-rich country?", "answer": "<b><u>Saud</u></b>i States (accept Kingdom of <b><u>Saud</u></b>i Arabia; accept Emirate of <b><u>Diriyah</u></b>; accept Emirate of <b><u>Najd</u></b> or <b><u>Nejd</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Scharf [[SHARF]] Children confessed to a blood libel in this country which contains the oldest institution which graduates Rabbis. A leader of an Aid and Rescue Committee in this country negotiated to trade the Kastner train of gold and diamonds for Jewish survival. This country passed three Anti-Jewish Laws during a period in which Mikl\u00f3s Horthy [[MEE-klohsh HOR-tee]] served as regent. Elie Wiesel [[VEE-zull]] was taken to Auschwitz from this country. For the point, name this country, whose capital contains a basilica named for and containing the right hand of this country's first king, Stephen.", "answer": "<b><u>Hungary</u></b> (accept <b><u>Magyarorsz\u00e1g</u></b>; accept <b><u>Hungarian</u></b> People's Republic or <b><u>Hungarian</u></b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Guerillas on this island used cow horns called <em>abeng</em> and caused rumors of trees that cut off heads. Quao [[KWAH]] led this island's Crawford's Town uprising, and Charles Lyttelton signed treaties on this island with Juan de Bolas. Captain Davy and Three Fingered Jack fought in this island's Tacky's War. Moore Town celebrates this country's Akan leader, Queen Nanny, and Edward Trelawny fought Cudjo in this country's Maroon Wars. For the point, name this former British colony, where Columbus spent a year after being shipwrecked in 1503.", "answer": "<b><u>Jamaica</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This artist filmed his friend, John Giorno, sleeping in his bed for his five hour and twenty minute long 1964 film titled <em>Sleep</em>. Another \u201canti-film\u201d by this person was <em>Empire</em>, which was comprised of eight hours of the Empire State Building viewed from a stationary camera. This artist\u2019s New York studio, frequented by celebrity artists, models, and rock stars, was known as \u201cThe Factory.\u201d Known for prophesying that \"in the future, everyone will be world-famous for fifteen minutes,\" for the point, who was this white-wigged American Pop artist?", "answer": "Andy <b><u>Warhol</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "While working in the Counter Intelligence Corps, this man hunted down Gestapo agents in Hanover. This man and the U.S. president contradicted Secretary of State William Rogers by planning a U.S. invasion of Cambodia. While National Security Advisor, this man undertook two secret visits to talk with Zhou Enlai [[ZHOH EN-LAI]], leading to the U.S.'s establishment of diplomatic relations with Communist China. For the point, name this Secretary of State who co-won the 1973 Nobel Peace Prize with L\u00ea \u0110\u1ee9c Th\u1ecd [[LAY-DUK-TAW]].", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Kissinger</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Hermann Giesler [[GEE-sler]] built this city's Gauforum [[GOW-for-um]] and Hotel Elephant. With Jena [[YAY-nah]] and Erfurt, this city forms the largest metropolitan area in Thuringia. Buchenwald [[BOO-ken-vahld]] concentration camp was located eight kilometers from this city in which Walter Gropius founded a system of \"comprehensive artwork,\" the Bauhaus [[BOW-house]]. Friedrich Ebert [[EE-behrt]] signed into law Germany's first democratic constitution that was named for, for the point, what city, which names a German Republic after World War One?", "answer": "<b><u>Weimar</u></b> (accept <b><u>Vimaria</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Debt after this war led to the Grace Contract loans, and Federico Blume developed the \"Submarine Bull\" for this war. Treaties leading up to this war included the Lindsay-Corral Protocol and the 1866 Boundary Treaty. This war included the Treaty of Defensive Alliance, which stemmed from the Monopoly Law. Beginning with the Battle of Topwater, this war included the Battle of Tacna and a clash of ironclads at Iquique [[ee-KEE-kay]]. For the point, name this war in the Atacama Desert between Chile, Bolivia, and Peru, fought over nitrate deposits near its namesake ocean.", "answer": "War of the <b><u>Pacific</u></b> (accept Guerra del <b><u>Pac\u00edfico</u></b>; accept <b><u>Saltpeter</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "To allow a Roman army to cross this river, Apollodorus [[ah-pah-loh-DOR-us]] of Damascus designed Trajan\u2019s Bridge. \u0110erdap [[DEHR-dahp]] National Park, named Serbia's first global geopark in 2020, protects lands on the banks of this river. This river formed the usual southern border of the ancient region of Dacia [[DAY-shuh]]. In 1831, politician Istv\u00e1n Sz\u00e9chenyi [[EESH-tvan SAY-tcheh-nyee]] devised a plan to open this river's Iron Gates gorge. For the point, name this major river which flows from the Black Forest to the Black Sea.", "answer": "<b><u>Danube</u></b> River (accept <b><u>Donau</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "During this event, the editorial \"It is Necessary to Take a Clear-Cut Stand Against Turmoil\" was published. Uyghur [[WEE-guhr]] leader \u00d6rkesh D\u00f6let [[WOOR-kesh DAH-vlet]] participated in this event. Support for those in this event was garnered at the Happy Valley Racecourse in Hong Kong. The death of Hu Yaobang [[YOW-BAHNG]] caused this event, which led to the purging of Zhao Ziyang [[ZHOH ZEE-YAHNG]]. Li Peng was able to suppress this event in cooperation with Deng Xiaoping [[SHAO-PING]]. The Tank Man photograph was captured during, for the point, what 1989 protests against the Chinese Communist Party?", "answer": "<b><u>Tiananmen Square</u></b> Protests (accept <b><u>Tiananmen Square</u></b> Massacre; accept <b><u>June</u></b> <b><u>Fourth</u></b> Movement; accept <b><u>'89 Democracy</u></b> Movement)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This novel's premise is that the author recovered a series of manuscripts, including a semi-fictional memoir written by the historical Gatien de Courtilz de Sandras [[gah-TYEN duh kor-TEE duh sahn-DRAH]]. In that historical memoir, this novel's primary protagonist visits Commander de Tr\u00e9ville [[truh-VEE-yuh]] and encounters some young men from B\u00e9arn [[BAY-arn]]. Cardinal Richelieu uses diamond studs to try to expose an affair between the Queen and Duke of Buckingham in this novel, in which D\u2019Artagnan longs to join the elite guards of King Louis XIII. For the point, name this novel by Alexandre Dumas.", "answer": "The <b><u>Three Musketeers</u></b> (accept <em>Les</em> <em><b><u>Trois Mousquetaires</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "William W. Cohen started one of these actions against Nazi Germany, leading to a 1933 event at Madison Square Garden. One of these events began after Nasir al-Din Shah of Qajar [[kah-JAR]] Iran granted G. F. Talbot a monopoly on tobacco. Fighting against Joseph Radetzky during Milan's Five Days broke out over one of these actions. One of these actions was carried out via the Continental Association, leading to the Restraining Acts. For the point, name these actions which occur when consumers choose not to buy certain goods.", "answer": "<b><u>Boycott</u></b>s (prompt on \"protest\" or similar answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During the May Offensive, an entire lane of this city's Newport Bridge was destroyed by a recoil-less rifle. In 1962, two disgruntled air force pilots bombed this city's Independence Palace as part of an assassination attempt. This city's police were called \"White Mice\" by American soldiers, because they wore uniform white helmets. Operation Frequent Wind was launched to evacuate this city during a 1975 battle. For the point, name this city which was renamed in 1976 for a former president after being captured by North Vietnamese forces.", "answer": "<b><u>Saigon</u></b> (prompt on \"H\u1ed3 Ch\u00ed Minh City\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle's namesake route was used by John Richards Lapenoti\u00e8re [[la-peh-noh-TYEHR]] and John Sykes to race back to Falmouth to relay an account of this battle. Occurring simultaneously to a land battle at Ulm, this battle included the death of an admiral whose final words were \"Thank God I have done my duty.\" Pierre Villeneuve [[vih-leh-NOOV]] led the French forces at this battle but was captured along with his ship, the <em>Bucentaure</em> [[boo-sen-TAHR]]. For the point, name this 1805 Napoleonic era naval battle off the coast of Spain, the last victory of Horatio Nelson.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Trafalgar</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this mountain range, <em>yatiri</em> folk healers sell goods at the Witches' Market to an ethnic group whose flag is known as Wiphala [[wih-FAH-lah]]. Irish geographer Joseph Barclay Pentland and English traveler Woodbine Parish surveyed the northern reaches of this range in the 1820s. The iron-hulled SS <em>Yavari</em> was launched on this range's largest lake in 1862 and is today a tourist attraction in Puno Bay. The Aymara and Quechua [[KEH-chwah]] live in, for the point, what extensive mountain range of South America?", "answer": "<b><u>Andes</u></b> Mountains (accept <b><u>Andean</u></b> Mountains)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This general committed suicide at the court of Prusias I of Bithynia [[bih-THIH-nee-yah]] after defeating Eumenes II [[YOO-meh-nees]] of Pergamon [[PEHR-gah-mun]]. This leader\u2019s assault on Saguntum [[sah-GOON-toom]] initiated a lengthy conflict with the Roman Empire. After his devastating victories at Lake Trasimene [[trah-SIH-mee-nee]] and Cannae [[KAN-nay]], this general appeared to be on the verge of ultimate victory, but his loss to Scipio [[SKIP-ee-oh]] Africanus at the Battle of Zama ended the Second Punic War.  For the point, name this Carthaginian general who led his war elephants across the Alps.", "answer": "<b><u>Hannibal</u></b> Barca (prompt on \"Barca\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Workers who acquire this resource around countries like Kuwait sing the <em>Fidjeri</em> [[feed-JEHR-ee]]. In Spanish Venezuela, workers who retrieved this resource were branded with a letter C, possibly standing for Cubagua [[koo-BAH-gwah]]. \"High bred\" ones of these items were found in the Sulu Archipelago of the Philippines, and the <em>Ama</em> work in Japan to obtain these items, one of which is named <em>La Peregrina</em>. Musical instruments and altarpieces were sometimes made out of nacre, the primary material of, for the point, what valuable objects found in mollusk shells?", "answer": "<b><u>Pearl</u></b>s", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Psychiatrist Fredric Wertham claimed that these products caused juvenile delinquency in his book <em>Seduction of the Innocent</em>. A book titled <em>Understanding</em> [these products] explored their history and artistic techniques and was written by Scott McCloud. One of these products, created by Joe Simon in 1941, depicts Adolf Hitler being punched in the face. Pioneering creators of these products include Jack Kirby and Stan Lee. For the point, name these products, works of popular literature which often depict heroes like Captain America.", "answer": "<b><u>Comic</u></b>s (or <b><u>Comic book</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Graphic novel</u></b>s; prompt on more general answers like \"books\")", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Historian Albert Terrien de Lacouperie [[al-BEHR tehr-RYEHN duh lah-koo-peh-REE]] claimed that this country's founding people were actually from Mesopotamia. In a story from this country, a flock of magpies formed a bridge to reunite the Cowherd and the Weaver Girl. Rulers of this country claimed legitimacy by invoking the \"Mandate of Heaven,\" and semi-mythical rulers of this country include the Yellow Emperor and Yu the Great. The earliest example of this country's writing system is preserved on oracle bones. For the point, name this home country of the semi-mythical Xia [[SHAH]] Dynasty.", "answer": "People's Republic of <b><u>China</u></b> (accept <b><u>PRC</u></b>; accept <b><u>Zh\u014dnggu\u00f3</u></b> or <b><u>Zh\u014dnghu\u00e1</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "George Ravenscroft helped trade this material in England, where George II passed a tax on this material in 1746. In medieval times, this material was made at Skalice [[skah-LEE-tzeh]] and Nov\u00fd Bor in Bohemia. Wadi El Natrun [[WAH-dee EL nah-TROON]] provided mineral soda to be combined with sand to make this material. <em>Lattimo</em> and <em>cristallo</em> were some of the forms of this material made on Murano Island in Venice. A stained form of this material was used in Romanesque cathedrals. For the point, name this translucent material often used for windows.", "answer": "<b><u>Glass</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man's coronation was marred by a massive stampede at Khodynka field. This ruler, who proposed the Hague Peace Conference, was almost killed by Tsuda Sanzo while traveling in Otsu, Japan. Later, this ruler's nation suffered crushing defeats in the Russo-Japanese War and World War One, destabilizing his government and leading to the February Revolution. For the point, what last Romanov tsar was executed alongside his family by the Bolsheviks in 1918?", "answer": "<b><u>Nicholas II</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man lost a wrestling match to Francis I at the Field of the Cloth of Gold. After his brother died, this man married his widow, a daughter of Ferdinand and Isabella. This ruler arrested Cardinal Wolsey for refusing to support his annulment from Catherine of Aragon, and later broke with the Catholic Church and created the Church of England after secretly marrying Anne Boleyn. For the point, what English monarch, the father of three other English monarchs, had six wives?", "answer": "<b><u>Henry VIII</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}